A Guide to the Richard E. Shope papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA199
Rockefeller Archive Center
Richard E. Shope papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1925-1971
Rockefeller Archive Center
Shope, Richard E. (Richard Edwin)
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA199
1 Cubic Feet
1 box(2 packages Collected Reprints).
Biographical/Historical note
Richard Edwin Shope; 1901-1966, physician and researcher in the field of virology at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, first in the Department of Animal Pathology at Princeton and later at the laboratories in New York City. He discovered the cause of swine influenza and anticipated a similar observation in humans; he identified the "mad itch" virus (disease in Midwestern cattle). He discovered two virus tumors of rabbits, one a fibroma and the other a papiloma which progresses to cancer. During the World War II he directed the work with rinderpest virus leading to development of a vaccine against this disease in cattle. His last work was in epidemiology and he worked with the natural history of three animal diseases and two virus diseases in deer.
Biographical note
1901 Born December 25 Des Moines, Iowa
1924 M.D. State University of Iowa
1924-1925 Instructor, pharmacology and materia medica, State University of Iowa College of Medicine
1925 Married Helen Ellis
1925-1930 Assistant Department of Animal Pathology Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, Princeton
1930-1934 Associate RIMR Animal Pathology
1934-1940 Associate Member RIMR Animal Pathology
1940-1949 Member RIMR Animal Pathology
1943-1946 Commander U.S. Navy
1949-1952 Associate Director Merck Institute
1952-1966 Member and Professor Rockefeller Institute and Rockefeller University, New York City
1966 October 2 Died James Ewing Hospital, New York City.
War Service
September 1942-April 1944 Director, War Disease Control Station, Grosse Ile, Province of Quebec. Worked on rinderpest leading to development of an effective vaccine.
1944-1946 Pacific area member of Naval Medical Research Unit #2 to go ashore and appraise medical hazards for troops ashore.
Honorary degrees
1936 M.S. Yale University
1951 V.M.D. University of Utrecht, Holland
1954 Sc. D. Rutgers University
1957 V.M.D. Justus-Liebig University Giessen, Germany
1958 Sc. D. University of Chicago
1959 Sc. D. University of Pennsylvania
1963 Sc. D. State University of Iowa
Awards
1936 Sigma Xi Semi-Centennial Research Award
1937 John Phillips Memorial Medal American College of Physicians
1938 Alvarenga Prize - College of Physicians
1943 John Scott Medal and Award, City of Philadelphia
1964 Legion of Merit U.S. Army
1947 Certificate of Accomplishment, State University of Iowa
1952 Anna Fuller Memorial Prize
1956 Commendation. Department of Conservation and Economic Development State of New Jersey
1956 Special Commendation. U.S. Department of HEW
1957 Kober Medal. Association of American Physicians
1957 Albert Lasker Award
1959 Bertner Foundation Award
1963 Howard Taylor Ricketts Memorial Award
1963 Special Citation. American Cancer Society
1965 New York Academy of Medicine Medal
Member: National Academy of Sciences, American Philosophical Society, Association of American Physicians, Society for Experimental Pathology, Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, Harvey Society, Sigma Xi, American Public Health Association, United States Livestock Sanitary Association, American Epidemiological Society, American Academy of Arts and Sciences.
Honorary Member: Eastern Iowa Veterinary Association, American Veterinary Medical Association, New York Pathological Soc., Royal Society of Medicine, Great Britain, Central New Jersey Veterinary Medical Association, American Board of Veterinary Public Health (Honorary Fellow)
Served on: Board of Scientific advisors - Jane Coffine Childs Fund for Medical Research, Scientific advisors, Merck Institute, Aftosa Technical Advisory Group, Pan American Sanitary Bureau, Zoonoses Technical Advisory Group, Pan American Sanitary Bureau, Board of Scientific Consultants, Sloan-Kettering Institute, Research Advisor Council, American Cancer Society, Vaccine Committee, National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, Committee on Naval Medical Research NRC, Board of Scientific Advisors, Jackson Memorial Laboratory, New Jersey Public Health Council, Chief, Biological Defense, New Jersey Civil Defense Agency, Panel on Animald, Committee on Biological Warfare, Research and Development Board, Department of National Defense, Consultant, Foot and Mouth Disease Research. Secretary of Agriculture, Technical Advisory Committee, New Jersey Civil Defense, Virus and Rickettsial Study Section, U.S. Public Health Service, Advisory Committee on Animal Diseases Transmissible to Man, New Jersey State Department of Health, Advisory Committee Berg Institute of Scientific Service, New York University, Cancer Advisory Board, Bureau of Biological Research, Rutgers University, Committee on Exotic Animal Diseases, USLA, Chairman, Advisory committee on Research on Etiology of Cancer American Cancer Society, Director, Commission on Epidemiological Survey, Armed Forces Epidemiological Board, Consultant to Surgeon General of Navy, Committee on Nationwide Eradication of Hog Cholera, USLSA, Scientific Advisory Committee, Grayson Foundation, Panel Chemical and Biological Warfare, President's Science Advisory Committee, Scientific Advisory Board, Walter Reed Army Institute of Research, Technical Advisory Panel, Biological and Chemical Warfare Secretary of Defense, Panel on Viruses and Cancer, National Advisory Cancer Council, Biological and Chemical Defense Planning Board, Chairman Research Advisory Council, American Cancer Society, Armed Forces Epidemiological Board, Consultant, Executive Office of the President - Special Projects, Commission on Epidemiological Survey, Armed Forces Epidemiological Board, Plum Island Animal Disease Lab - U.S. Department Agriculture Advisory Committee, Lobund Advisory Board, Notre Dame University, Technical Committee on Poliomyelitis Vaccine U.S. Public Health Service, Board of Medical Education and Research, University of Penn. (also Association Trustee), Science Advisory Committee, National Better Business Bureau, The National Foundation, Committee on Virus Vaccines, Consultant Illinois Zoonoses Research Center, Chairman, Section of Pathology and Microbiology NAS, Board of Scientific Counselors, National Cancer Institute, Committee on Science and Public Policy, NAS, NAS/NRC advisory committee on Foot and Mouth Disease, Scientific Advisory Committee, New England Regional Primate Research Center.
Arrangement note
Arranged in chronological order.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 Sh77
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, biographical correspondence, photographs, administrative correspondence, bibliography, collected reprints.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Life sciences; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Biology -- Research; Medicine, Preventive; Biochemistry; Medical sciences; Medical research; Diagnostic virology; Viruses -- Research; Cancer; Cancer -- Research; Tumors in animals; Animals -- Diseases; Swine influenza; Influenza; Epidemiology; Rinderpest virus; Aujeszky’s disease; Medical education; Diseases; Epidemics; Shope, Richard E. (Richard Edwin); Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- Bibliographies, 5" letter size GL 3/86. [Reprocessing] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1926-1953 December, 8 pp.
  - 1926-1957, 9 pp.
  - 1926-1966, 17 pp [annotations in pencil by Ruth Sternfeld, RU Archives]
- Biographical General, 1935-1965
  - Biographical note, 1935 October 31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - From Who's Who in America, 1942-1944; Photocopy (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Peyton Rous. "Presentation of the Kober Medal to Richard Shope", pp 29-37 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Richard Shope. "Acceptance of the Kober Medal for 1957", pp 38-40 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Transactions of the Association of American Physicians 70 (1957) 29-40, Reprint (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Science Service, 1963 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents note
    Listing of Dr. Shope's scientific achievements, awards and honorary degrees.
  - E.H. Kone/R.E. Shope re biographical information for award, 1964 December 28; 5 pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Encl.: 11 January 1965, Richard E. Shope biographical information
  - Peyton Rous. "Citation of Presentation of The Academy Medal to Richard E. Shope, MD" (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bulletin of the New York Academy of Medicine 41 (1965) 400-403, Photocopy. [Reprint in Folder 15] (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Biographical General, 1967-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Obituaries for R.E. Shope from the New York Times and unidentified newspaper, 1966 October 3; Photocopies (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Helen E. Shope/Sidney A. Britten [re] R.E. Shope memorial minute from Members of the Armed Forces Epidemiological Board with copy, 15 May 1967 memorial minute, 1967 June 15 1967 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - R.P. Mason/D.W. Bronk [re] 1968 January-February issue of CA 18 (January-February 1968) 40-41, 1968 March 28; Copy of publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    R.N.G. [Ronald M. Grant], "To Helen - A Footnote to Medical History"
  - Colin M. MacLeod/Maclyn McCarty, 1971 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of items re R.E. Shope from RI/RU Quarterly 1957-1961
  - C.H. Andrewes, "Biographical Memoir. Richard Edwin Shope (1901-1966)" American Philosophical Society Yearbook, 1971; pp 179-184. Photocopy (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Medical World News, pp 45-49, 52-53, 57. "Human Genetic Engineering", 1973 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes re Shope papilloma virus. Page clippings from publication.
  - RU News and Notes 8 (1977) 3-4. "Background on History. Swine Flu Virus" (Box 1, Folder 3)
- N.A.S. Memoir "Richard Edwin Shope 1901-1966. A Biographical Memoir" by Christopher Andrewes, 1979; Reprint (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Biographies Rockefeller Institute, 1962 January-1964 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  [Corrected and revised 6/1963]
- Biographies: "Statement Concerning Scientific Work of Richard E. Shope", circa 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  [This appears to be one of the autobiographical accounts written at request of Dr. Gasser ca 1953. C. Kopp].
- Biographies, undated, mixed dates (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Includes other material.
  - American Men of Science, 9th Edition, undated
  - Citation for Legion of Merit
  - Record Cards
  - From Business Manager Files, circa 1953
    Includes 5 pp of autobiographical account requested by Dr. Gasser
  - Who's Who in America, 1942-1944
- Biographical. Photographs - Portraits, 1928 1936 1953 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  WWII in uniform
- Photographs. Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Biennial symposium on virology in honor of Wendell Stanley, 1966 January; 4 color snapshots
    Identified by Ruth Sternfeld.
  - R.E. Shope (Lt. Commander) collecting snails on Okinawa
    (Identified by G.W. Corner but not used in History)
  - Perspectives in Virology IV, Barbizon Plaza Hotel, New York City, 1966 February 3-4
    Group photograph with some identification on back of photograph.
- Administrative Correspondence, 1925-1969 (Box 1)
  - 1925-1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Scope and Contents
    Select individual items include but are not limited to:
    - R.E. Shope employment application to RIMR, 1925 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Shope/Francis G. Blake. Acknowledging letter of appointment as Assistant in the Department of Animal Pathology, RIMR at Princeton dated 25 April 1925, 1925 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Exchange between S. Flexner, C. Ten Broeck, R.E. Shope, E.G. Smith re financial arrangements for Shope to 1936 International Congress for Microbiology in London, 1935 April 30-1936 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Various newspaper clippings, re Shope tracing origin of transmission of human influenza to hog virus and earthworm, 1939 July-August (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Shope/A.R. Dochez. re R.E. Shope promotion to Member, RIMR as of 1 July 1940, 1940 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - C. Ten Broeck/H.S. Gasser re John Scott Medal Certificate and Premium to Dr. Shope for "Discovery of the Complex Etiology of Swin Influenza", 1943 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - R.E. Shope/RIMR Board of Scientific Directors, 1948 July 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Letter of Resignation from RIMR as of May 16, 1949
  - 1950-1955
    - Shope/A.R. Dochez, re Shope appointment to RIMR as of July 1, 1952, 1951 December 4 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1956-1959
    - Shope/D.W. Bronk re visits to laboratories in Russia. Handwritten, 1956 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - D.W. Bronk/Shope re honorary degree to Dr. Shope on occasion of 350 anniversary of the Justus-Liebig Hochschule, University of Giessen, 1957 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - B. Pedersen, Science/E.H. Kone re Kober medal and honorary Sc. D. to Dr. Shope, 1957 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - H. Mantell/Shope re Lasker award to Shope and WCBS Radio interview, "This is New York" by Jim McKay on vaccines for viruses, 1957 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Eugene Kone/PHS-NIH, re Dyer lecture at NIH by Shope on influenza, 1957 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - C.R. Read/E. Kone re lecture by Dr. Shope at February 8?, 1958, Chicago ACS meeting, 1958 January 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - re honorary degree to Dr. Shope in Chicago, 1958 March 20 1958 June (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Shope/Douglas H. Whitaker re Shope presentation, August 1958, Stockholm, International Congress for Microbiology, 1958 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 30 September 1959, University of Pennsylvania News Release re honorary D. Sc to Dr Shope, October 3, 1959, at 75th anniversary of School of Veterinary Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia for major contributions in the field of comparative medicine and Shope presentation, "Comparative Medicine", 1959 September 30 1959 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Includes reprint of address.
  - 1960-1963
    - Shope/W.R. Flinn [re] Shope's bout w/ Eastern equine encephalomyelitis, 1960 January 6; Photocopy (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Includes New York Herald Tribune, 9 January 1960 clipping.
    - R.E. Shope, "An Account of the Infection of Richard E. Shope with Eastern Equine Encephalomyelitus Virus", 1960 January 6; 4 pp of photocopies signed by Dr. Shope (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - [re] Symposium on Eastern Viral Encephalomyelitis, School of Veterinary Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa, 1960 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Includes Press Reports, and reports re Shope's survival from encephalitis. Also includes R.E. Shope, as Chairman, "Summarization of Symposium on Eastern Viral Encephalomyelitis. (9 pp text of Shope's summary of symposium)
    - D.W. Bronk/Shope re Shope election to membership in Century Association w/Shope acknowledgment, 1960 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Excerpt from Science re R.E. Shope becoming member of the National Cancer Institute Board of Scientific Counselors, 1961 July 21; Typescript (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - exchange re Shope receiving honorary degree, State University of Iowa, 1963 April-May 1963 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - re Dr. Shope receiving Howard Taylor Ricketts Memorial Award, University of Chicago, 1963 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Announcement of, and biographical information re Dr. Shope.
    - Morris Pollard/D.W. Bronk, and 4, N.Y.C., 4th Symposium "Perspectives in Virology" sponsored by the Gustav Stern Foundation of New York on Hidden Viruses" honoring Dr. Shope, 1963 July 30 1964 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      [See also: Folders 9,15]
    - Iris Klein, ACS/E.H. Kone re request for photograph of Dr. Shope for receipt of ACS award, 1963 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1964-1969
    - re Perspectives in Virology IV, The Gustav Stern Foundation "World's Leading Virologists in Symposium on "Hidden Viruses". News release and program, 1964 January 9 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      [See also: Folders 9, 14]
    - Peyton Rous, "Citation and Presentation of the Academy Medal to Richard E. Shope, M.D. and R.E. Shope, "Acceptance of the Academy Medal" Bulletin of the New York Academy of Medicine 41 (April 1965) 400-403, 1965 April; Reprint (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Exchange between D.W. Bronk, David Rockefeller and Dr. Shope re Shope's illness and residence facilities for the Shopes' on the RU campus with Shope reply to David Rockefeller, 1966 April 19-September 2 1966 June 6; (carbon copy) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Telegram to RU Board of Trustees reporting Dr. Shope's death on 2 October 1966, 1966 October 3; Carbon copy (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - [re] R.E. Shope's death, 1966 October 3-December (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes:
      - Telegram to RU Board of Trustees, 1966 October 3; (copy)
      - News from the Rockefeller University, 1966 October 3
      - D.W. Bronk/RU Faculty, 1966 October 3
      - Father Theodore Hesburgh/D.W. Bronk; Bronk reply, 12 October, 1966 October 6
      - D.W. Bronk/Helen Shope, 1966 October 23
      - Helen Shope/David Rockefeller, 1966 November 3
        Photocopy. 17 November 1966. L.G. MacNamara/RIMR re Shope resolution; D.W. Bronk thank you 7 December
      - Helen Shope/D.W. Bronk re Father Hesburgh and Shope's books and papers, 1966 December 20
- Collected Reprints, 1926-1961 (Package 1-2)